[SPEAKER_01]: What did you have in mind?
[SPEAKER_01]: So, I was thinking, in the last talk, we were turning your world upside down.
[SPEAKER_01]: Venerable Udayi was, as a patujana, thought to himself, what if I were to turn upright
[SPEAKER_01]: The upside-down-ness of the five aggregates.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you were saying, in order to do that, you cannot deny.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just turning the self and the aggregates round, it's not about denying the self.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not about, shall I say, not acting out of it, not denying it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But allowing it to endure and recognizing it as an enduring phenomenon.
[SPEAKER_01]: And... and you...
[SPEAKER_01]: I think you sort of suggested that there's, you know, there's a kind of... that that's the most difficult thing for a... for a patujan to do.
[SPEAKER_01]: But there are, you know, certain characteristics of that sense of self.
[SPEAKER_02]: Ah, the most difficult is to see the sense of self.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, to see, to pick up on, okay, that's what the sense of self is.
[SPEAKER_02]: See it as a phenomenon, as a thing that endures.
[SPEAKER_02]: My sense of self is such and such, or... Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Even if you can't define it, that is its characteristic.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: It cannot be defined, but it's real as such, as a non-definable, ambiguous thing.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because if there is absolutely no sense of self whatsoever, you... there would be nothing to talk about.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, yes.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you can either say...
[SPEAKER_02]: If Putrajana learns how to see the sense of self, he can then eventually see the right order of the aggregates through that sense of self.
[SPEAKER_02]: Not in response to, not as a means of dealing with the self, but literally just through the sense of self, you see the basis upon which that sense of self depends.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that basis is not in your control.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, seeing the basis as impermanent, seeing the basis as suffering, means the experience is that not-myself.
[SPEAKER_02]: And, alternatively, I suppose, learning how to see two simultaneous things, enduring at the same time.
[SPEAKER_02]: You can only attend one, but that means you can know the other.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, learning what the knowledge is, it's also a way in the same direction.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because when we talk about two simultaneous things, I bet many people would think like, oh, so I have to think of two things at the same time, to balance the extent of them.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's literally now, while we are speaking, the body is enduring.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Oh, but I didn't think about it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_02]: But you know it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, rediscovering, rediscerning that which you already know, that it's there, enduring, simultaneously with other things you're attending to, that's that's how you create a basis for discerning that sense of self.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you mean...
[SPEAKER_02]: The characteristics of the sense of self are something you can attend to on the basis of an enduring sense of self.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: But if you have absolutely no grasp of such a philological principle, there's nothing for you to see, because all you see is what you put in front of you.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's where people struggle, like, understanding the sense of self, because for them, understanding means being able to put my finger on it.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's not understanding.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's you attending to it.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's you informing yourself, collecting data.
[SPEAKER_02]: But none of that is on the level of understanding, which is always peripheral to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, understanding is being...
[SPEAKER_01]: Something that you're not.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're not attending to.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're not.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's a definition of an insight as well.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or like, say, when, like, fully understanding something.
[SPEAKER_01]: When you, when you... Well, you know, like, imagine any problem.
[SPEAKER_02]: You're trying to understand a problem.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, you're attending to the, to the components.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Things that constitute a problem.
[SPEAKER_02]: You're collecting information about it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: But that's not understanding.
[SPEAKER_02]: And you know that that's not understanding.
[SPEAKER_02]: And you can have a lot of information.
[SPEAKER_02]: And you can even make sense out of it, to some extent.
[SPEAKER_02]: But still, you know it's not understood, because the problem is still there.
[SPEAKER_02]: Now, imagine, while you're making that effort to figure out all this information about the problem,
[SPEAKER_02]: And then you get it.
[SPEAKER_02]: You wouldn't get it if you haven't been attending to these things as a problem, as something that needs to be understood.
[SPEAKER_02]: But you certainly did not get it simply by attending to these things mechanically.
[SPEAKER_01]: You got it because you understood it.
[SPEAKER_02]: So that's what I mean.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's not like, oh, so you can't do understanding directly.
[SPEAKER_02]: But if you attend to the right things rightly, and know what you're supposed to understand, that's how you're closer to getting understanding.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you know you understand it when you don't need to do anything about it anymore.
[SPEAKER_02]: You don't need to... Yeah, of course.
[SPEAKER_02]: Once it's understood, it's understood.
[SPEAKER_02]: You can question that understanding.
[SPEAKER_02]: You can try and sort of put it to test, so to speak, like revisit it, maybe, see if it really holds the water in every regard.
[SPEAKER_02]: But, yeah, to some degree, you understood that.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, am I free of suffering on account of my understanding?
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, I'm not sure.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, maybe I haven't understood enough, haven't cultivated what I did understand, haven't... Because that's the measure.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's not like that you think you understood.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's when you can't suffer anymore on account of your understanding.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because of your understanding, you're free from suffering.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, for as long as that's not developed, you have to keep pushing that same understanding.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's the same, like, as we started, the sense of self.
[SPEAKER_02]: You're not understanding the ambiguity of the sense of self.
[SPEAKER_02]: And you will not understand the ambiguity of the sense of self for as long as you think that understanding is on the level of clarifying information about the ambiguity.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's not.
[SPEAKER_02]: Only to some extent.
[SPEAKER_02]: You need to know what you're supposed to understand, but for most people understanding, as I said, it's more like
[SPEAKER_02]: When you can define things, have it on your own terms, put your finger on it, then it's regarded as if it's understood.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because, look, it's all clear.
[SPEAKER_02]: I've broken down, I've systematized, systematized all this information about
[SPEAKER_02]: I sent a selfie and all these charts and stuff.
[SPEAKER_02]: Oh, so it's... now I just need to get it and I got it all laid out.
[SPEAKER_02]: I memorized it and it's understood.
[SPEAKER_02]: No.
[SPEAKER_02]: And the more you think that that's understanding, the less likely you'll be able to actually understand it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because you're going in the opposite direction of understanding.
[SPEAKER_02]: You're collecting information about it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, isn't it... do you not think it's worth...
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, considering what are the various, kind of, characteristics that the sense of self has.
[SPEAKER_02]: In itself, it's meaningless.
[SPEAKER_01]: Doing that.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, if you know why you're doing it, because you want to get understanding, then yes, of course.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, I mean, the view behind, the motivation behind determines it, whether it's helpful or not.
[SPEAKER_02]: Not, oh, just do this blindly and it will be helpful for you.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: The only thing you can do blindly, that will be helpful for you, is keep the precepts.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Just do that.
[SPEAKER_02]: But everything else, it depends why you're doing it and to what extent.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, sometimes people will be...
[SPEAKER_02]: Okay, so I'll just attend to the characteristic of the sense of... because they're trying to get rid of the discomfort.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you're not understanding.
[SPEAKER_02]: You're just using it to... acting out of the same type of craving.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you won't understand the nature of it.
[SPEAKER_02]: What is the nature?
[SPEAKER_02]: As the Buddha said, the nature of the self is that it's not yours.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's not yourself.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, that's what needs to be understood on the basis of that sense of self.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you have to stop denying the sense of self, because how can you understand it?
[SPEAKER_02]: If you're trying to get rid of it, if you're ignoring it, if you're indulging it, if you're basically engaging with it.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, first, you have to develop that restraint, recognize that there is a sense of self, that is a problem because of which you suffer.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, now, within that sense of self, you want to see how that is not yours.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's the understanding you pursue.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, yes, if you're doing it for those reasons, then you would be investigating characteristics, the signs and tokens, as the Buddha would say, because they are coming now against the background of the right context.
[SPEAKER_00]: Is... is investigation like... is that in a... in a... like... is that the means which you can develop an understanding, but you also have to understand that's not complete understanding?
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, that's the closest to... to... to something that you can do in order to develop understanding.
[SPEAKER_02]: But, eh... if you... if you want to do rightly,
[SPEAKER_02]: Your investigation must not lose the sight of itself.
[SPEAKER_02]: And by that, I mean, you should already... by wanting to investigate, you should begin investigating why do you want to investigate.
[SPEAKER_02]: Not like, oh, I'll do investigation, I'll find these random things that the suttas talk about, so I'll investigate, I'll ponder about it, in these, like, psychological terms.
[SPEAKER_02]: No, I've found these things, I want to investigate.
[SPEAKER_02]: Okay, stop.
[SPEAKER_02]: Why?
[SPEAKER_02]: Why do I want to investigate?
[SPEAKER_02]: What is the problem?
[SPEAKER_02]: There must be a problem, in my experience as a whole, that I'm trying to overcome by practicing the dhamma, by investigating, by doing what the suttas say.
[SPEAKER_02]: What is that problem?
[SPEAKER_02]: So, investigation basically starts and it never really leaves that basis of clarifying what the actual problem is.
[SPEAKER_02]: Being very... understanding what the problem is would then get you to understand what the solution is.
[SPEAKER_00]: And dukkha.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, dukkha.
[SPEAKER_02]: But again, okay, so what is dukkha then?
[SPEAKER_02]: Do I know?
[SPEAKER_02]: Have I understood it?
[SPEAKER_02]: Or is it just any kind of genetic notion that I sort of have, concept of, ah, dukkha.
[SPEAKER_02]: Okay, dukkha.
[SPEAKER_02]: But what is dukkha for me?
[SPEAKER_02]: So, understand that, and there you go.
[SPEAKER_02]: Through your investigation, through, like, investigating your own motives, you got to investigate now the nature of the suffering, and that's certainly much closer to
[SPEAKER_02]: Enabling you to understand the nature of suffering, which is the first noble truth.
[SPEAKER_02]: This is suffering.
[SPEAKER_02]: Ah, okay.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you realize then that people are not free from suffering, not because they haven't done things rightly.
[SPEAKER_02]: No, it's because they simply don't understand even what suffering is.
[SPEAKER_02]: Amidst of them suffering, they still don't understand what suffering is.
[SPEAKER_02]: But often people would assume
[SPEAKER_02]: We kind of already... simply by suffering, you know what suffering is, and now it's just a question of performing a set of prescribed rules and observances and techniques and methods and motions, and you will then travel out of the world of suffering.
[SPEAKER_02]: No.
[SPEAKER_02]: That travel begins by first actually understanding that you don't know what suffering is.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because the moment you understand what suffering is, you understand what the escape from it is.
[SPEAKER_02]: You understand what the cause of it is.
[SPEAKER_00]: You won't be acting out of it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, you understand the Four Noble Truths.
[SPEAKER_02]: The only reason you're acting out of it is because you're affected by it.
[SPEAKER_02]: And you're affected by it because you don't understand it.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, that's another thing.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, you could... You arrived at, oh, so I want to practice dhamma because suffering is the problem.
[SPEAKER_02]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, what would be the characteristics of that suffering?
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you can take that in various directions, but, for example, now, as how we started this, you can ask, say, can you suffer without a sense of self?
[SPEAKER_02]: Without any self-awareness, can you experience dukkha, if self-awareness is not there?
[SPEAKER_00]: If there is no self-awareness?
[SPEAKER_00]: Awareness of this body and experience?
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, awareness of yourself.
[SPEAKER_02]: Recall any suffering that you had, that for you would be the closest representative of what you think dukkha is.
[SPEAKER_02]: Is there a perception of yourself there?
[SPEAKER_02]: Can you be unaware of yourself while you're suffering?
[SPEAKER_00]: You would be aware of yourself if there was suffering, yes.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, can you have suffering without self-awareness?
[SPEAKER_02]: No.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, it's impossible.
[SPEAKER_02]: Can you have feeling without self-awareness?
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, it's always a sense of self.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you... feeling can be experienced, but you cannot have feeling.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like... What do you mean?
[SPEAKER_00]: Like assuming feeling.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, feeling is the tone, the mood,
[SPEAKER_00]: Of your experience is...
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean, of the experience is still there, but you do not assume that experience of feeling or of the mood.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, then, the feeling is not there, if you're not assuming it.
[SPEAKER_02]: You can't have two perspectives at once.
[SPEAKER_02]: You're speaking now as if you're both Putujanan and an arahant.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that doesn't work.
[SPEAKER_02]: You're either one and or the other.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you can't say you have a feeling, but you're not assuming the feeling.
[SPEAKER_02]: For you, the only feeling you know is the feeling that's being assumed.
[SPEAKER_00]: Don't the aggregates continue to persist, though?
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, how would you know that?
[SPEAKER_02]: How can you see that for yourself?
[SPEAKER_02]: The only way to see how can aggregates persist is to become an arahant, which means your current aggregates will not persist, because your current aggregates are top to bottom affected by upādāna.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's why we would say matter would cease feeling everything.
[SPEAKER_02]: All the aggregates would cease when you become enlightened.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because when he speaks to a patujana from his point of view, yes, everything that he has assumed will cease to be so.
[SPEAKER_02]: But sure, if you step back from both and assume the situation theoretically, yes, aggregates persist.
[SPEAKER_02]: But how?
[SPEAKER_02]: To what extent?
[SPEAKER_02]: You can either continue thinking it theoretically or recognize that that situation does not apply to you.
[SPEAKER_02]: Thus, it's not accurate.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, for you, feeling, perception, any aggregate that you know is already assumed.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's the whole problem.
[SPEAKER_00]: But to say that there is no more aggregate, like, is not...
[SPEAKER_02]: Yes, there is no more aggregate.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that...
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean, would that not be denial?
[SPEAKER_02]: Like... like... there's no more form... Well, in the broadest sense, sure, it's a denial.
[SPEAKER_02]: But your denial is determined by your motivation.
[SPEAKER_02]: Not by actually saying there are no aggregates.
[SPEAKER_02]: Death is not a denial for an arahant.
[SPEAKER_02]: Cessation is not a denial.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's why you're doing the cessation.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, if you are saying there are no more aggregates, there are no more aggregates, because you're basically just trying to manage the pressure that current assumed aggregates are putting onto you, so you're just dismissing the problem, yeah, then yeah, that's a denial.
[SPEAKER_02]: But it's not a denial because of the dismissal, it's denial because of your intention behind it.
[SPEAKER_00]: I guess what...
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean, I've read often that there's the arahant, you know, he's awakened and he's developed the full extent of knowledge, but then he... there's remainder... there's still remainder left.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that remainder left is the aggregates.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, see, you got the idea about it now.
[SPEAKER_02]: And, eh... you have two options.
[SPEAKER_02]: You can either leave that idea as it is, and think it... that it represents what arahant is, or you can then start questioning that idea and say, well, if you really understood an arahant, you would be at least a sotāpanna.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, are you a sotāpanna?
[SPEAKER_02]: If the answer is no to that, means your idea of what arahant is, is not an accurate idea.
[SPEAKER_02]: Nobody denies that there is an idea there, but you mustn't leave it for what it is because, okay, it makes sense.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, but are you a Sotāpanna on account of that sense?
[SPEAKER_02]: No.
[SPEAKER_02]: Means it's not an accurate idea.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's what I mean.
[SPEAKER_02]: You have a degree of understanding, but it's because you don't push the understanding, that's why you don't get freedom from suffering as a result of the understanding.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's not because you haven't, you know, found all the right understandings and so on, or you haven't been doing it long enough.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you got the idea about an arahant, but it cannot accurately represent it, because you're still putujana.
[SPEAKER_02]: It cannot accurately represent the state of an arahant.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, make more effort than to understand what kind of... what is the residue in the case of an arahant.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then, if that understanding frees you from suffering, you know you're on the right track.
[SPEAKER_00]: I suppose my understanding of the aggregates is...
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean, that would be insufficient.
[SPEAKER_02]: What do you mean?
[SPEAKER_00]: Like...
[SPEAKER_00]: I can...
[SPEAKER_00]: If there's a conscious body, the aggregates must be there.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, that's... Well, see, that's what it is.
[SPEAKER_02]: If there is a conscious body, aggregates must be there.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, experience, all of experience, is through the aggregates.
[SPEAKER_02]: Again, saying, if there's a conscious body, aggregates must be there, implies that, on account of your conscious body, you know the aggregates.
[SPEAKER_02]: But conscious body, it's already where the aggregates are.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, being alive.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, having a conscious body means, within that notion of conscious body, that you can relate to, that's where you discern the aggregates.
[SPEAKER_02]: You don't infer the aggregates.
[SPEAKER_02]: On account of having a conscious body, thus, the aggregates must be there.
[SPEAKER_02]: Having a conscious body means the aggregates are there as that conscious body.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, within the basis, within the context of conscious body, you can then discern more of an aspect of material or emotional or whatever, within the basis of conscious body.
[SPEAKER_02]: Not kind of in response to.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if there...
[SPEAKER_02]: But again, why would you want to discern the five aggregates?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because we were mentioning before, I mean, my understanding isn't complete, but there was the idea that an arahant has no more aggregates.
[SPEAKER_00]: A fully enlightened being
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's why you're still not an arahant.
[SPEAKER_00]: Finding out how is that possible will make you at least a sarpana.
[SPEAKER_02]: But see, thinking that there is a thread that unites you with the state of an Arahant that you can think accurately, is why you're not understanding what an Arahant is.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because that thread stands in place of what you think understanding of an Arahant state is.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's often people struggle with that.
[SPEAKER_02]: Thinking that, oh, I know I'm not Sotāpanna, I'm a Bhutujana, but my practice is helping me, which means I am somehow, in some manner, to some extent, on some level, getting closer to Arahantship.
[SPEAKER_02]: You don't have a clue.
[SPEAKER_02]: Only Sotāpanna can know.
[SPEAKER_02]: Okay, now I know exactly what the way is.
[SPEAKER_02]: And I can either pursue it or not, but he knows.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, unless there is a right view, you should not trust any understanding that you have.
[SPEAKER_02]: Doesn't mean you should mystify it or pretend, oh, it's just, you know, it's not about understanding.
[SPEAKER_02]: It is about understanding.
[SPEAKER_02]: But it's about sufficient understanding.
[SPEAKER_02]: Sufficient being at least the understanding of the right view.
[SPEAKER_02]: But see, for as long as you think now that your idea of Arahant's aggregates is accurate,
[SPEAKER_02]: You're not going to make effort to understand.
[SPEAKER_02]: How can an arahant not have aggregates and have aggregates?
[SPEAKER_02]: Because you think you figured it out.
[SPEAKER_02]: And now you're just about, you know, threading water and doing this or doing that, and somehow you get closer to that... that state.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, yes, from Putujan's point of view, arahant has no aggregates.
[SPEAKER_02]: There's no being there.
[SPEAKER_02]: Bhāva has ceased.
[SPEAKER_02]: He does not exist.
[SPEAKER_00]: I thought it was the cessation of assuming.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sure.
[SPEAKER_00]: That upādāna.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yes, theoretically, it is cessation of assuming.
[SPEAKER_02]: But, for you, as we discussed with the order, everything is through that assuming.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you can't think accurately, how would things be without assuming, because you're thinking that with your assuming.
[SPEAKER_00]: I thought the...
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean...
[SPEAKER_00]: I thought that there would be aggregates and no assuming.
[SPEAKER_00]: That would be how... there would be aggregates.
[SPEAKER_02]: Sure.
[SPEAKER_02]: Again, theoretically, extrapolated from your experience, it doesn't apply to you anymore.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, that's not an accurate thought.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because now, any notion of aggregates you have, even Arahant's aggregates, free from assuming, are your aggregates affected by assuming.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you can't have
[SPEAKER_02]: the accurate thought of arahant aggregates, while you're still a putujana.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's just impossible.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because your thoughts are affected by your assuming.
[SPEAKER_02]: Thus, anything within those thoughts is equally affected by assuming.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just looking at paticca-saṃgupādāna, you got, like, eh...
[SPEAKER_01]: He talks about, you know, vedanānirodha, the cessation of feeling, which is...
[SPEAKER_01]: You know, understood by someone who sees the dhamma.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the cessation of feeling is the cessation of the aggregate.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sure, sure.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, it's the cessation of all...
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: But just that, if you just, like... if you...
[SPEAKER_01]: If you've got this idea of the aggregates continue for the arahants, then what does that mean?
[SPEAKER_01]: The cessation of feeling while he's alive?
[SPEAKER_01]: You know, there's a flag there that says, OK, something's not understood.
[SPEAKER_02]: Oh, yeah, there are lots of flags.
[SPEAKER_02]: But the reason why people ignore the flags is because it's quite frightening to now recognize that
[SPEAKER_02]: Even the most accurate ideas that you have about dhamma and the state of anarahant and everything, you're still fully enclosed within that sort of sinking ship of your ignorance.
[SPEAKER_02]: But, if you actually are able to accept that idea, that's how you can find a way out.
[SPEAKER_02]: If you don't, that will be the reason why you won't find a way out.
[SPEAKER_02]: Doesn't matter how much other effort you put in your practice.
[SPEAKER_01]: The understanding is so enticing, because, you know, basically things make sense.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, and that's exactly how it should be.
[SPEAKER_02]: Things make sense, but then you question that extent of that sense you made.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, okay, so this makes sense, but am I free from suffering?
[SPEAKER_02]: Is the lust diminishing in me?
[SPEAKER_02]: Aversion?
[SPEAKER_02]: Desire for distraction?
[SPEAKER_02]: Are all these things disappearing as a result of my understanding?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, I don't really know.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, then you should not trust your understanding.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, just trusting that fact that things make sense.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: You have to kind of...
[SPEAKER_02]: Okay, that makes sense.
[SPEAKER_02]: Let me see if I can make more sense out of it.
[SPEAKER_02]: And more sense, and more sense, and more sense.
[SPEAKER_02]: And all of it converges on that vedanāna.
[SPEAKER_02]: Even this whole thing of, oh, you know, trying to understand the aggregates, get the idea of what arahant's aggregates are, then, you know, trying to approximate it, whatever.
[SPEAKER_02]: Why?
[SPEAKER_02]: Because you don't want to suffer.
[SPEAKER_02]: Which means, you feel right here, right now, your non-freedom in regard to suffering.
[SPEAKER_02]: You're still liable to it.
[SPEAKER_02]: So then, if you stay within that context, your thinking will cease to be theoretical.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because you're still within the...
[SPEAKER_02]: Okay, so this is the measure.
[SPEAKER_02]: This is the container within which whatever I'm trying to do, or understand on account of the dhamma, should be understood.
[SPEAKER_02]: Within me being liable to...
[SPEAKER_02]: So, liability to suffering.
[SPEAKER_02]: What are the characteristics?
[SPEAKER_02]: How does that feel?
[SPEAKER_02]: How would then understanding of the aggregates free me from this suffering?
[SPEAKER_02]: But often people start with, yes, of course, I want to be free from suffering.
[SPEAKER_02]: Then, ah, aggregates need to be understood.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then you go there and completely forget and abandon the context of why you're doing it in the first place.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's how you become, eh...
[SPEAKER_02]: You start thinking about dhamma on purely abstract terms.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then people kind of understand.
[SPEAKER_02]: Oh, well, this is just too abstract.
[SPEAKER_02]: This doesn't really pertain to suffering.
[SPEAKER_02]: But then they will go too far the other way.
[SPEAKER_02]: Oh, just stop thinking.
[SPEAKER_02]: Stop reading the suttas.
[SPEAKER_02]: Stop.
[SPEAKER_02]: Just sit and meditate and your citta will open up and whatever else.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because they kind of understood that this is abstract, it doesn't work.
[SPEAKER_02]: But they haven't understood that you can also learn how to think not abstractly.
[SPEAKER_02]: You can think on the basis, on the... within the container of your feeling and that motivation to be free from suffering.
[SPEAKER_02]: But that's a skill that needs to be discerned right in the middle there.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, it's usually either you overthink it and it becomes just abstract and you divorce yourself, which is a definition of abstraction, you divorce yourself from that basis of feeling, or then you just completely dismiss the domain of thinking, which is ironically another thought, on account of which you just start to mystify the present moment and here and now, judgment-free mind, embodiment and whatnot.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then refuse to think, refuse to make the effort to understand.
[SPEAKER_02]: Either way, you fail to understand what needs to be understood.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you overshot the mark, then you undershot it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Does that maybe bring us back to the idea of the sense of self?
[SPEAKER_01]: Bringing, bringing...
[SPEAKER_02]: The feeling, like, you know... Well, I think, actually, that's probably more... even more accurate for something what Puṭācārya should do, is never lose the context of his feeling, present enduring feeling.
[SPEAKER_02]: Within that, you will discern the signs of your mind.
[SPEAKER_02]: Within that, you will discern the signs of yourself.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Of your sense of self, of your sense of I am, of your sense of master, controller.
[SPEAKER_02]: Within the feeling you're subjected to.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, then, if you want to choose a contemplation, so to speak, in terms of the suttas, what needs to be understood, you choose the ones that will least likely result in you being distracted from what you're feeling right there, right now, while you're contemplating it.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, don't think about the third jhāna in relationship to the base of nothingness, because you're still a patujana that doesn't even know the... doesn't even have a mundane right view.
[SPEAKER_02]: And yet, here you are, wanting to understand all these eight jhānas.
[SPEAKER_02]: Again, understand.
[SPEAKER_02]: In other words, you're just acting out of craving to have things laid out, figured out, in a sense that you want them to be.
[SPEAKER_02]: You know, putting your finger onto it, it's basically always rooted in craving, even on that mental level.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, why do I want to understand five and a half jhānas?
[SPEAKER_02]: Ah, because I want to practice Buddhism.
[SPEAKER_02]: Why do I want to practice Buddha's teaching?
[SPEAKER_02]: Because I'm away from suffering.
[SPEAKER_02]: Which suffering?
[SPEAKER_02]: Am I suffering right now?
[SPEAKER_02]: No, but I am liable to suffering.
[SPEAKER_02]: Ah, so it's right here, right now.
[SPEAKER_02]: Liability to suffering, it's always present.
[SPEAKER_02]: I'm always within it.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's always my reality.
[SPEAKER_02]: And on account of that, I'll forget about it, and then I'll go and figure these random things out.
[SPEAKER_02]: Then, I realize, oh, this doesn't work.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's just thinking.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, on account of wanting to be free from suffering, I will abandon that awareness of that liability, in order to dismiss the thinking, and then mystify my present moment.
[SPEAKER_02]: Either way, you basically conceal the problem.
[SPEAKER_02]: Although you started with the problem, with the recognition of it.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, that's what I mean.
[SPEAKER_02]: The idea you have of the five aggregates of an arahant,
[SPEAKER_02]: Have it in you, think about it, and also allow your liability to suffering to be there, discerned.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, is your idea freeing you from that liability?
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, I don't know.
[SPEAKER_02]: Means, it's not.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you're doubtful about it, it's not freeing you from it.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's not clear.
[SPEAKER_02]: Thus, it cannot be magically freeing you from it, unless you know it.
[SPEAKER_02]: So then, take that, develop that idea further, until it fully binds and connects, goes right through the center of that liability to suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that liability to suffering is that... it's wanting feeling.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's felt.
[SPEAKER_00]: To be what I wanted.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, no, no.
[SPEAKER_02]: Or just felt.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's just felt.
[SPEAKER_00]: Being within feeling.
[SPEAKER_02]: You can try and define it all you want, that will all be secondary to the fact that it's felt.
[SPEAKER_02]: And how is it felt?
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_02]: How?
[SPEAKER_00]: There are only three ways you can feel a feeling.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, how is it felt?
[SPEAKER_02]: Always unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's the definition of dukkha.
[SPEAKER_02]: Literally means dis-ease, unease.
[SPEAKER_02]: Sukha is ease.
[SPEAKER_02]: Dukkha is opposite of ease.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's the thing.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you're not... you don't need to suffer right here, right now, in terms of something really affecting you.
[SPEAKER_02]: A mere recognition that you are liable to suffer and you cannot even fathom how could you defend yourself from it.
[SPEAKER_02]: You have no access to that exposure to suffering.
[SPEAKER_02]: You just recognize it that is so.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's dukkha.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then, that dukkha is the chief of all the dukkha.
[SPEAKER_02]: All other suffering you can experience has to come within the basis of that liability to suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: That liability of feeling, like, like how that one sutta says, like, even in pleasant feeling, it's painful, seeing it as painful.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_02]: Painful as a thought.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, you're liable, you're liable to suffer.
[SPEAKER_02]: Thus means any, any feeling, any change in the feeling can be that suffering, which means any feeling is that suffering, because you're liable to feel it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Can you be liable to suffering if you don't feel anything?
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: Impossible.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, liability to suffering for you means liability to feeling.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, that's why if you cherish, entertain, welcome, delight in, act out of feeling that you want, makes you equally then liable to feelings that you don't want.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because you can't just have half of the feelings and not the other half.
[SPEAKER_02]: Impossible.
[SPEAKER_02]: The only way to free yourself from liability to suffering is to free yourself from liability to feeling.
[SPEAKER_02]: And you free yourself from liability feeling by, you know, being restrained, not acting out of the feelings, and then understanding the nature of an arisen feeling, whatever that feeling is.
[SPEAKER_01]: And once you see that, that involves the fact that all feelings come before any sense of self.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: You don't even have to think about sense of self in this particular regard.
[SPEAKER_02]: If you just recognize the liability of feeling enduring.
[SPEAKER_02]: Oh, I feel okay now, but I'm not saying it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Thus, I will not have saying when that changes.
[SPEAKER_02]: And it will have to change, one way or the other.
[SPEAKER_02]: And what if it changed for worse?
[SPEAKER_02]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_02]: What if it changed for better?
[SPEAKER_02]: You have no control either way.
[SPEAKER_02]: You are subjected to it.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, how can you free yourself from something you have no control over?
[SPEAKER_02]: Firstly, by understanding why there is a problem with it.
[SPEAKER_02]: There is a problem with it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because sometimes people say, oh, well, okay, it's just so.
[SPEAKER_02]: The feeling is just so.
[SPEAKER_02]: Only arahants can say that.
[SPEAKER_02]: But we don't start as arahants.
[SPEAKER_02]: We start as bhattacharyas.
[SPEAKER_02]: Thus, your feeling is just so, means my feeling is just so, and it's a problem for being just so.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you don't want to mystify it, but you certainly don't want to abstract yourself from it either.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, not being in control of your feelings, why is that a problem?
[SPEAKER_00]: I can...
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm affected.
[SPEAKER_00]: I could be affected at any time.
[SPEAKER_00]: Even when I have a pleasant feeling arise, it only lasts a certain period of time.
[SPEAKER_00]: If I want more of it, and I can't get more of it, well then, I suffer on account of that.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, because of... the problem is... the problem of not being in control of feeling is because you'll be affected.
[SPEAKER_02]: Why is that a problem?
[SPEAKER_02]: Why being affected by feeling is a problem?
[SPEAKER_00]: Being affected is... it's painful, because I can't...
[SPEAKER_02]: I can't choose to stop.
[SPEAKER_02]: Okay, yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, that's even more accurate.
[SPEAKER_02]: Being affected, it's painful.
[SPEAKER_02]: Why is pain the problem?
[SPEAKER_00]: The pain is a problem.
[SPEAKER_02]: Why is pain a problem?
[SPEAKER_02]: It is a problem.
[SPEAKER_02]: But why?
[SPEAKER_02]: Why is it a problem?
[SPEAKER_00]: Sometimes...
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean, I guess...
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm thinking of degrees of pain, but I feel that's not the same.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, we're talking about the pain, doesn't matter what degree.
[SPEAKER_02]: Why is pain a problem?
[SPEAKER_00]: Being affected by it.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what I can tell.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm exposed, I'm vulnerable, I'm susceptible to it.
[SPEAKER_02]: And all that is a problem because it's painful.
[SPEAKER_02]: Being exposed, vulnerable, susceptible, what they all have in common is that they are uncomfortable.
[SPEAKER_02]: Discomfort means pain.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, we're back on to why is pain a problem.
[SPEAKER_02]: And the pain is a problem always and only for one reason.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's because you want to get rid of it.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, the pain is not a problem.
[SPEAKER_02]: Problem is not in the pain.
[SPEAKER_02]: The problem is in you always automatically not wanting it.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, that's what the problem is.
[SPEAKER_00]: Your attitude.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, can you be susceptible to something without that being painful?
[SPEAKER_02]: Would being susceptible to something be a problem if it's not painful?
[SPEAKER_02]: No.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then, would something be painful if you're not trying to get rid of it?
[SPEAKER_02]: If you're not craving against it?
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_02]: So then, the problem is your craving.
[SPEAKER_02]: Not the pain.
[SPEAKER_02]: Not the lack of control.
[SPEAKER_02]: Not being susceptible.
[SPEAKER_02]: Not being liable.
[SPEAKER_02]: None of these things are a problem.
[SPEAKER_02]: The problem is your craving of not wanting it.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, when non-control is a problem,
[SPEAKER_02]: It's only so because you still crave control.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's why, like, the mindfulness, recollectiveness of death is like a direct, the quickest, the sharpest way as well.
[SPEAKER_02]: Towards arahantship, literally.
[SPEAKER_02]: Have a thought of dying the next moment, next inbreath.
[SPEAKER_02]: Are you affected by it?
[SPEAKER_02]: If you are, it's not because of death or anything that can befall you.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's because you're resisting to accept it, resisting, craving against it.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's why, again, the first Noble Truth, understanding what suffering is, this is what suffering... that's... that's... this is that understanding.
[SPEAKER_02]: You realize suffering is not in the pain.
[SPEAKER_02]: Pain is not suffering.
[SPEAKER_02]: But for Putujita, for another life and mind, there is no pain without suffering.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because there is no pain without craving against the pain.
[SPEAKER_02]: But the suffering is in the craving.
[SPEAKER_02]: Why?
[SPEAKER_02]: Because if suffering were in the pain, removal of pain would mean removal of suffering.
[SPEAKER_02]: But it's not.
[SPEAKER_02]: But if suffering is in the craving, if you remove the craving, yeah, you have pain in... because you don't always suffer when you experience pain, by the way.
[SPEAKER_02]: If I tell you, oh, if you endure some, I don't know, physical discomfort for 10 minutes, and then you'll be rewarded by 60 billion dollars, and a life of luxury, and you never have to work a day in your life, that pain will be joyful for you, because you know what's at the end of it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Or, as the Buddha would say, if you practice, if you endure the pain of restraint, you'll be rewarded with, like, heavenly rewards, lives of luxury and joy.
[SPEAKER_02]: Then, that pain...
[SPEAKER_02]: But if the pain is always suffering, you would suffer.
[SPEAKER_02]: You would not accept that deal, because pain is always suffering.
[SPEAKER_02]: But it isn't.
[SPEAKER_02]: You know, every time you go to work, or you have to hold your duty, that's all painful, that's all uncomfortable.
[SPEAKER_02]: But you don't resist it, because you have a bigger picture in your mind, that this contributes towards that bigger picture, which is picture of pleasure.
[SPEAKER_02]: Even being... even wanting the freedom from suffering is the picture of pleasure.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's just a natural principle.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's how it works.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, suffering is not in the pain.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because if it were so, there would be no self-awareness of it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Whenever there's pain, there's suffering, absence of pain, absence of suffering, absence of liability to suffer as well.
[SPEAKER_02]: And you would not have a recognition of it.
[SPEAKER_02]: But the fact is that suffering is in your craving towards pain.
[SPEAKER_02]: See, if I tell you if you endure this pain for 10 minutes and then you have a exponential reward, you won't crave against the pain.
[SPEAKER_02]: You will want that pain, because you want the reward.
[SPEAKER_02]: And you won't suffer in regard to the pain.
[SPEAKER_02]: Although, you would suffer if I tell you, I just tricked you, I'm not giving you the reward.
[SPEAKER_02]: And, without inflicting any physical pain on you, and you would suffer on account of it, more than you suffer on physical pain being inflicted upon you.
[SPEAKER_02]: Why?
[SPEAKER_02]: Because your craving determines the suffering.
[SPEAKER_02]: First, you were not craving against it.
[SPEAKER_02]: You were not craving against the pain, but you were very much craving for
[SPEAKER_02]: The great reward.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, craving is present in regard to the reward.
[SPEAKER_02]: I tell you there is no reward.
[SPEAKER_02]: Your craving is there.
[SPEAKER_02]: You suffer because of your craving.
[SPEAKER_02]: You want to protect your reward because of your craving.
[SPEAKER_02]: You want to defend it.
[SPEAKER_02]: You will cry on account of it if you lose it because of the craving.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, pain is the problem because of your craving.
[SPEAKER_02]: Thus, pain is not a problem.
[SPEAKER_02]: Your craving is the problem.
[SPEAKER_02]: But saying that now,
[SPEAKER_02]: For somebody who is not free from craving, saying, okay, so pain is not the problem, well, that's an idea.
[SPEAKER_02]: But if that idea is not freeing you from suffering, as in not freeing you from craving, means pain is the problem for you.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because you don't know how not to crave, in regard to the pain.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, that's what I mean.
[SPEAKER_02]: Sometimes people get a hint that, oh, suffering is not in the pain, but then overly accept any feeling that comes their way.
[SPEAKER_02]: Okay, so, this is just so.
[SPEAKER_02]: There is no problem in this.
[SPEAKER_02]: Just accept it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Just let it go.
[SPEAKER_02]: Can you let go of you, of your idea of letting go?
[SPEAKER_02]: Can you really let go of that?
[SPEAKER_02]: You see, I'm letting go of all of this.
[SPEAKER_02]: It still allows me to have at least some sense of control.
[SPEAKER_02]: I'm just practicing letting go.
[SPEAKER_02]: A sense of control is a sense of craving.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you're letting go of your cravings, with your craving.
[SPEAKER_02]: And usually, those people get very upset, if that view is challenged.
[SPEAKER_02]: They might not get upset on account of things they're letting go, but if the view of that letting go is challenged, they get upset, they defend it, because their view is in their control.
[SPEAKER_02]: And on account of that, they suffer.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, it's not an accurate application of your effort, in other words.
[SPEAKER_02]: You want to apply your effort whereby what you are letting go is resulting in freedom from suffering in every regard.
[SPEAKER_02]: Not just in this particular little corner it works, but if anything else changes, if somebody challenges it, I'll be affected, I'll be emotionally disturbed on account of it.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, how would you not crave for pain?
[SPEAKER_02]: That's what liability to pain is.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's what liability to suffering is.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's inability to not crave.
[SPEAKER_00]: Just think of the stock answer.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Abandon craving.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, craving is not a matter of choice.
[SPEAKER_02]: But, at the same time, it's something you're responsible for.
[SPEAKER_00]: As long as I'm not an arahant, I'm responsible for craving.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: And when it arises... Well, you're never free from craving.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because you always feel something, which means you always crave something in regard to feeling.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's why craving is not in regard to... only in regard to pain.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's in regard to the domain of whatever's felt.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, if you feel pleasant, you will automatically crave towards it.
[SPEAKER_02]: If you feel unpleasant, you will automatically crave away from it.
[SPEAKER_02]: If you feel neither, well, you will automatically crave towards distracting yourself from it.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, how can you stop that automatic craving?
[SPEAKER_02]: Because you are responsible for it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Craving is not part of the aggregate.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's not part of the things that arise for you.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's your attitude towards it.
[SPEAKER_00]: By stopping... refusing to... stopping...
[SPEAKER_02]: So, but why would you want to stop the denial of feeling?
[SPEAKER_02]: What would be your motivation behind that?
[SPEAKER_00]: To deny it.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you want to stop the denial.
[SPEAKER_02]: Your wanting to stop denial is rooted in denying the craving.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because how are you affected by craving?
[SPEAKER_02]: As I said, craving doesn't arise.
[SPEAKER_02]: In the same sense, feelings arise for you.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, what is there to stop?
[SPEAKER_01]: Do you have an idea on this?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, your understanding, your attitude towards it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, I was thinking...
[SPEAKER_01]: Towards what?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, towards the order.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what I was thinking.
[SPEAKER_01]: Go on.
[SPEAKER_01]: So... Let's stick with the feeling and craving.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what I mean.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, eh...
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you can't attend to craving.
[SPEAKER_02]: Craving is not an object of your mind.
[SPEAKER_02]: Oh, I see my craving.
[SPEAKER_02]: But for as long as you think that you can control... Craving is peripheral in regard to whatever is presently felt.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: But for as long as you keep the understanding that you can affect the feeling, you can change it, you have a right to...
[SPEAKER_01]: Not want this feeling to be there.
[SPEAKER_02]: Right, yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because those are two different things, by the way.
[SPEAKER_02]: You can change your feeling.
[SPEAKER_02]: I mean, sensuality has effect.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Ill-will has effect.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's not like, oh, it's completely has nothing to do with anything.
[SPEAKER_02]: It works.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's the only way that Puthujjana knows of working.
[SPEAKER_02]: But the thing you refer to is like, you have a right to do so.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's a different thing.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's already on the level of the view.
[SPEAKER_02]: I have a right to interfere with this feeling, which means I have a right to crave against the feeling or for the feeling.
[SPEAKER_02]: And for as long as you don't abandon the view that you have a right to do so, you will be automatically doing it so.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, only through going against the grain of that view, that I have a right,
[SPEAKER_02]: You will stop doing it.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's how you stop that automatic response of craving.
[SPEAKER_02]: By ceasing to provide maintenance for it.
[SPEAKER_02]: And this view that you have a right to do so, is how you maintain the attitude of craving of doing so.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, abandon the view that you have a right towards pleasurable feeling, towards unpleasant feeling, towards neutral feeling.
[SPEAKER_02]: You don't have a right.
[SPEAKER_02]: Whichever feeling is there, you are subjected to it.
[SPEAKER_02]: You have no rights over it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're within it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're sub... yeah, that's what I want to say.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're... you are kind of subordinate to that feeling.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that cannot change.
[SPEAKER_02]: Any change that you can inflict, so to speak, is within.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Is within that...
[SPEAKER_02]: The feeling that is enduring.
[SPEAKER_02]: ...which fully contains you.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: That you have to endure.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, stop giving in.
[SPEAKER_02]: To the means of changing feeling on account of what's felt.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's how you will stop perpetuating craving.
[SPEAKER_02]: I don't understand that.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's not something, oh, here is a recipe, just stick to these rules and these methods.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because different, literally, different whenever you become recollect of the present moment, there is a feeling enduring there, which means there's going to be an attitude towards it.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's the attitude you need to be dealing with.
[SPEAKER_02]: Not the theory of the attitude that I must deal with.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, what are you feeling right here, right now?
[SPEAKER_02]: Neutral.
[SPEAKER_02]: What is... are you... are you aware of it?
[SPEAKER_02]: Are you losing the sight of that neutral?
[SPEAKER_02]: Are you being distracted towards other things?
[SPEAKER_02]: That's your work, then.
[SPEAKER_02]: Oh, I feel unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_02]: Is there an implicit attitude that I should not feel this?
[SPEAKER_02]: I have a right to not feel this.
[SPEAKER_02]: I'm entitled to not feel this.
[SPEAKER_02]: I can't wait for it to go away.
[SPEAKER_02]: All these thoughts are exemplification of the attitude that I am first and this is just here temporarily.
[SPEAKER_02]: I must get rid of it one way or the other.
[SPEAKER_02]: Even I will endure it for the rest of my life.
[SPEAKER_02]: Why?
[SPEAKER_02]: Oh, because I don't want it to be here.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's that.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not what you do on account of it.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's whether you feel...
[SPEAKER_02]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_02]: Why?
[SPEAKER_02]: Why you're doing it, which will reveal whether you feel entitled to get rid of it, or have it, or whatever.
[SPEAKER_02]: And you will, for as long as you're not aware of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you can act on account of it, but...
[SPEAKER_00]: There's a difference between acting on account of it, under the impression that I am in control of it, and under the impression that I'm not in control.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, it's not my right to be... Well, it depends what acting on account of it means.
[SPEAKER_00]: If it's skillfully.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not... like if it's not against the precepts, not against the training.
[SPEAKER_02]: Right, right, right, right, right.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, that's the thing.
[SPEAKER_02]: If it's not against the precepts, if it's not against the training, you're not really acting out of it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Acting out of it means acting for the purpose of either getting more of this feeling or getting rid of this feeling.
[SPEAKER_02]: But, that only applies on the level of the body, and that's not where the feeling is rooted.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you have to start by not acting out of it, as in not going against the precepts.
[SPEAKER_02]: But then... See, it's not against the precepts to go alone and sit... be alone in your kuti and sit quietly.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, it's not on the level of unwholesomeness of breaking the precepts.
[SPEAKER_02]: But you might be well doing it for very unwholesome reasons.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you can't just say, oh, it's just a question of not acting out of it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Not acting out of it first, to contain yourself, but then it's a question of understanding whatever current feeling... whatever current feeling is and whatever your attitude towards it is.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you might be on paper wholesome because you're always secluded in your kuti and so on, but the true reason for that might be because you hate everybody else.
[SPEAKER_02]: You can't stand other people.
[SPEAKER_02]: Everything is a disturbance.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you just want to find the environment that's in your control.
[SPEAKER_02]: My kuti.
[SPEAKER_02]: If somebody comes and tells you, get out of there, could you?
[SPEAKER_02]: Would you remain indifferent and equanimous?
[SPEAKER_01]: Or would you be disturbed?
[SPEAKER_02]: So, what you need to do is know the motivation in regard to your present enduring feeling.
[SPEAKER_02]: And not lose the sight of it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Ever.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because that's where acting out truly is.
[SPEAKER_02]: In not... in ignoring that degree of that motivation behind.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because as I said, I will not act out of my feeling.
[SPEAKER_02]: Why?
[SPEAKER_02]: Oh, because I want to get rid of it.
[SPEAKER_02]: So now, for me, getting rid of the feeling is abstaining from getting rid of the feeling.
[SPEAKER_02]: And you can never...
[SPEAKER_02]: Okay, always look at your motivation.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's your method.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, I suppose you can say that, but... Why do I want to do that?
[SPEAKER_02]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, why am I doing that?
[SPEAKER_02]: Which means, always has to be discerned on the basis of a recollected present experience as a whole.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because that's where the motivation is.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's where the feeling is induced.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's where the moods are.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, now, while you're trying to figure out what I'm saying,
[SPEAKER_02]: Why?
[SPEAKER_02]: Ask yourself.
[SPEAKER_02]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, why is this important to be understood?
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's how you'll understand what I'm saying.
[SPEAKER_00]: To be free from suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: To be free from...
[SPEAKER_02]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, why do you want to be free from suffering now?
[SPEAKER_02]: Is it because that already implies you're not free?
[SPEAKER_00]: It implies that I'm not free from suffering.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, how does that implication manifest in your experience?
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, you're not free from suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: How's that?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because feeling is felt.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, how is that?
[SPEAKER_02]: Oh, I'm not free from suffering.
[SPEAKER_02]: Is that a concern for you?
[SPEAKER_02]: Is concern unpleasant?
[SPEAKER_02]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_02]: Is displeasure a problem?
[SPEAKER_02]: Is this... Is pain a problem?
[SPEAKER_00]: A craving.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the problem.
[SPEAKER_00]: Craving is a problem in regard to pain.
[SPEAKER_02]: Obviously, you can't have craving without the pain or without a feeling.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, through going through this, basically, almost like drills of reflection, you keep hammering in the context that pain while endures, or feeling while it endures, it's not a problem, but there is no problem without the feeling.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's how you get to then discern the aptitude, peripherally, to the problem of the feeling.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's what I meant, upādāna is not in the five aggregates.
[SPEAKER_02]: But there is no upādāna without the five aggregates being there.
[SPEAKER_02]: But usually, when people think about holding and attachment, whatever you want to translate it, it just becomes another thing, another thing I can attend to, focus on, say no to, choose it.
[SPEAKER_02]: No.
[SPEAKER_02]: You can do that with things that aggregates present you, but upādāna is not in them.
[SPEAKER_02]: Nowhere, in nothing, not in between, not in response, nothing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yet, without aggregates, there is no upādāna.
[SPEAKER_02]: But if you look at the aggregates, you're not gonna see upādāna.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's completely peripheral from your look of the aggregates.
[SPEAKER_02]: Same with the feeling.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's what I mean.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, you can't see your craving.
[SPEAKER_02]: You can't say no to your craving, because that's not craving.
[SPEAKER_02]: You're craving that.
[SPEAKER_02]: Craving is peripheral to present enduring feeling.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, discern, recollect, present enduring feeling, as I said.
[SPEAKER_02]: Oh, well, suffering is... not being in control is a problem.
[SPEAKER_02]: Why?
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, because I'm liable to it.
[SPEAKER_02]: It implies I can suffer.
[SPEAKER_02]: Oh, how is that?
[SPEAKER_02]: Oh, well, that's felt as a concern.
[SPEAKER_02]: What is a concern?
[SPEAKER_02]: A concern is an unpleasant feeling that endures.
[SPEAKER_02]: Ah, so I'm craving against the...
[SPEAKER_02]: I wouldn't have a problem with concern if by some whatever reason it's not felt unpleasantly.
[SPEAKER_02]: Any problem you have in the world, any problem you had, you would have, you will have, it's only a problem for one reason.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's felt unpleasantly and you not crave against it.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, concern is not a problem.
[SPEAKER_02]: Anxiety is not a problem.
[SPEAKER_02]: None of these things are a problem.
[SPEAKER_02]: Pain is the problem, because you cannot... you don't know how not to
[SPEAKER_00]: Those are just symptoms, or... Those are just further results.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then we realize the pain is not the problem either.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's my craving that's the problem.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's why I suffer.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's what Buddha said.
[SPEAKER_02]: Presence of craving means presence of suffering.
[SPEAKER_02]: Absence of craving, absence of suffering.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's simultaneous.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, whenever there is a suffering present in me, means craving is present in me, to the extent that there is suffering.
[SPEAKER_02]: Whenever there is no suffering present in me, then there is no craving present in me.
[SPEAKER_02]: Usually, people regard it in the linear sense of craving is a matter of choice.
[SPEAKER_02]: You just say no to it, say no to it, and somehow down the line, your feelings will wither away, and then you'll be free from everything.
[SPEAKER_02]: No.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because you're craving for that, because you're unaware of your motivation in regard to why you're doing it in the first place.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, when I asked you the other day in that talk, are you liable to suffering?
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Why is that a problem?
[SPEAKER_02]: How does that feel?
[SPEAKER_02]: And it's like, oh, I feel such a... right here, right now.
[SPEAKER_02]: Ah, so, if you don't feel suffering on account of right here, right now, liability to suffering, would you then suffer on account of anything that can come through that liability?
[SPEAKER_02]: Impossible.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you uprooted the feeling.
[SPEAKER_01]: The recognition of my liability to suffering is not a problem anymore.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why is it a problem?
[SPEAKER_02]: The only reason this is a problem is because
[SPEAKER_02]: I don't know the escape out of suffering, which is another way of saying, I don't know how to stop craving.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's where the Four Noble Truths is.
[SPEAKER_02]: Once you understand what the true problem is, which is not the pain, it's the craving in regard... that's where the problem is.
[SPEAKER_02]: You then understand that absence of that means absence of the problem.
[SPEAKER_02]: Regardless, even if the people come and, you know, start chopping your limbs and abusing you and everything else, you will not suffer, because suffering was never in those things.
[SPEAKER_02]: Suffering is not in the aggregates.
[SPEAKER_01]: In the same sense, upādāna is not in the aggregates.
[SPEAKER_02]: You can even ask yourself, why is the... why is the... why is the pain of interrogation unpleasant?
[SPEAKER_02]: Why is it unpleasant?
[SPEAKER_02]: Because you came against the pain of it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because... You crave against the pain of it.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, it's suffering because you crave against it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Not because in itself it's suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: I guess, and there's also the motivation
[SPEAKER_00]: No, you have to start like that.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's what Buddha meant.
[SPEAKER_02]: What was it?
[SPEAKER_02]: Craving is to be abandoned by the means of craving, conceit by the means of conceit.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you crave now to be free from craving.
[SPEAKER_02]: As a result of that craving,
[SPEAKER_02]: You will hopefully do the right... like, understand the right things, make the right effort, that will then result in cancelling that very craving.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's exactly what I'm describing.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, because you want to be free from suffering, you start to question the nature of the feeling, and then you get to realize that suffering is not in the feeling, it's in the attitude in regard to that feeling, and then you get to realize that that attitude is not a matter of your choice, but more like a matter of your secondary choices that result in feeding that attitude.
[SPEAKER_02]: Choices towards pleasure, choices towards no pain, acting out of it.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you stop doing that and you stop feeding the suffering.
[SPEAKER_02]: Feeding the craving, sorry.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's how you destroy the craving.
[SPEAKER_02]: On account of the very craving.
[SPEAKER_00]: Feeding the craving is feeding the suffering.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, of course.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's literally synonymous.
[SPEAKER_02]: Craving?
[SPEAKER_02]: Endured presence of craving, peripherally, as the attitude of your mind?
[SPEAKER_02]: Attitude of craving is felt as suffering.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's the same thing.
[SPEAKER_02]: Not like, oh, there is craving and then there is suffering.
[SPEAKER_02]: There's one thing.
[SPEAKER_02]: Attitude of craving that's felt suffering.
[SPEAKER_02]: As suffering.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, removing the attitude of craving cannot anymore result in feeling suffering.
[SPEAKER_02]: But the reason... see, it's so hard... well, it's so easy, because the attitude is invisible.
[SPEAKER_02]: As I said, you can't attend to your craving.
[SPEAKER_02]: You can't see, oh, this is my craving.
[SPEAKER_02]: You only feel suffering.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then, when you look, all you see is things in front of you.
[SPEAKER_02]: I see this, I see that.
[SPEAKER_02]: Thus, natural response, response with the grain of that deception, is
[SPEAKER_02]: I suffer because he said that.
[SPEAKER_02]: I suffer because I lost this.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_02]: There is losing of this and suffering simultaneously present.
[SPEAKER_02]: But it's a mistake of the, like, fundamental proportion to assume that because they're simultaneously present, that's why this is suffering.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's the nature of ignorance.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's why even a vijja cannot be in the aggregates, cannot be in things you perceive or feel or intend.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's inrigate.
[SPEAKER_02]: But it cannot be found anywhere else, except where those things are.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because how can you mistake your suffering for something you perceived, or even for the feeling you felt, if feeling and perception were not there?
[SPEAKER_01]: There's nothing to be mistaken with.